<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Impartial account of the nature and tendency of the late addresses, in a letter to a gentleman in the countrey</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46115</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12647853</idno>
  <idno type="VID">65195</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240991363</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing I73A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32361</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12647853</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46115)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65195)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1528:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Impartial account of the nature and tendency of the late addresses, in a letter to a gentleman in the countrey</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:65195:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65195:1"/>
            <head>An Impartial Account, of the Nature and Tendency, of the late <hi>ADDRESSES;</hi> in a Letter to a Gentleman in the Countrey.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. YOU are not mistaken in taking it for granted, that I have read the several late <hi>Addresses</hi> to His Majesty, for being the Subject of the chief diversion of the Town, I should have been unfit for conversation, had I not so far consulted them, as to be able, as well as others, to make them the matter of discourse and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment among my Friends. But whereas you are further plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to require my inward and serious thoughts concerning them, I must crave liberty to tell you, That notwithstanding all your Interest in, and Authority over me, you should never have been able to have extorted from me what you desire, did not the Service which I owe His Majesty and the Government, command more at my hands, than the friendship and deference which I pay you could have obliged me unto. So that you are to ascribe my compliance with your request, to its falling in with the Fealty and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance which I render my Prince. And the more Freedom, and less Reserve, you find me to use upon this Subject, you are intirely to resolve it into the Love and Compassion which I bear for the King, who I fear, is not only industriously deluded, but wofully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed, by the judgment which some about him pretend to make of the sense and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the People from these Addresses.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. For no Applications of this nature to the <hi>Regnant</hi> person are to be esteem'd of any great weight or significancy, if you do but consider the Result of the many Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresses Three and twenty year ago to <hi>Richard Cromwell,</hi> and how they only served to render him secure till he was undermined and supplanted. For of all the <hi>Sixteen hundred thousand</hi> that vow'd to Live and Dye by him, not so much as one man drew a Sword in his favour when he came to be laid aside. I acknowledg, that there is a great difference betwixt an <hi>Usurper</hi> and a <hi>Rightful Sovereign;</hi> yet that detracts very little in the present case, from the importance of the consideration which I have suggested: seeing the least that we are to gather from it, is this, That no Addresses contrary to the interest and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral humour of the Nation, are to be accounted of any value for a Prince to sustain himself upon. And if there be nothing else to secure our late Addressers to His Majesties service, but their Promises and Protestations in those Papers, he may be as much disap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed should he have occasion to trust to them, as the former Gentleman after the like security was.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. It is astonishing, as well as surprising, that when <hi>Petitions</hi> had been not only dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenanced, but forbidden by Proclamation, <hi>Addresses</hi> should so soon after be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged and promoted! And our amasement is greatly heightned, when we consider that the <hi>Petitions</hi> were in reference to matters which every body understood, and in relation to such things wherein the Law justified the Petitioners; whereas the <hi>Addresses</hi> respect matters which very few understand, and which the Law noways authoriseth private men to meddle with, and which none save a Parliament have Power or Ability to decide and determine. For tho' men are to be esteem'd capable of knowing their own wants, fears and dangers, and ought to be justified in begging those means of Relief and Redress which the Law hath provided for them; yet every one is not to be accounted suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently qualified to determine concerning the Reasonableness and Legality of Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Proceedings and Resolves; nor is any number of men whatsoever, empowered to Umpire differences between His Majesty and His great Council. And whereas those ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Petitions</hi> which seem'd most peremptory, did nevertheless, with all due resignation reserve to His Majesty his full Prerogative, many of the <hi>Addresses</hi> import no less than the Robbing the Parliament, not only of their Right and Authority to Impeach Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, censure Offenders, withhold, as well as give supplies, but of their most essential Priviledge, <hi>viz.</hi> freedom of Debates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. Nor doth it appear to considering Persons, that any advantage can arrive to the King or Government by them; wheras the mischiefs and inconveniencies which do attend them, are obvious to every one. For what else do they tend unto, or can they be supposed calculated for, but to divide the Nation into factions and parties, and to foment those heats and animosities among His Majesties Liege people, which are already too
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:65195:2"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65195:2"/>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:65195:3"/>great to need to be farther heightned and enflamed? 'Tis His Majesties desire, as well as his interest and duty, to be equally esteemed the Father and Defender of all his people; but these Addressers would possess the Nation, that they only are to be accounted His Loyal Subjects; and that all His favours are only due, and ought to be confined to them: And by threatning the generality of people, that they have forfeited His Majesties affection and care, by refusing to act as they do; they insensibly lessen the love which His Majesty ought to have in the hearts of all His Subjects, and wonderfully abate the zeal which they would otherwise have for his Service. Nor can any say, that Petitions have the same effects, seeing amongst persons in the same circumstances, some may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present their wants and grievances, without prejudicing or giving offence to those who chuse silently to undergo them. And who knows, but that whil'st some think they are to seek their Relief by humble Applications unto, and fervent Importunities of their Prince; there may be others who hope, that their Soveraign may from the sense which he hath of their Calamities, afford them, at last, all the succour he can, without the soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citation of their cries? But the nature of these Addresses being to commend and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud the present posture of affairs, and to justify most of the steps and councels by which we have been reduced into this doleful condition; they do in effect declare every one to be peevish and clamorous, that cannot acquiesce and rejoice in this state of things under which we groan and labour. And as they hereby render all those enemies unto them, whose safety and happiness they are conceived, not only to abandon, but destroy; so the very Government, through the characters of Grace and Favour which it placeth upon their Applications, runs a hazard of losing much of its respect and veneration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. And besides this and many other mischiefs, which they do naturally involve the Government and the Kingdom under; they will be found prejudicial and inconvenient to the King, in the tendency which they have to deceive and abuse him. For whereas they are designed to perswade His Majesty, that what they represent and suggest, is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and universal sense of his people, and that he may accordingly take his measures; it is both evident in it self, and will be found so in the issue, that they contain and express only the sentiments of a few persons of little interest, and most of them of a very small &amp; mean figure in the Nation. For if Elections of Members to serve in Parliament, be the best standard to judge the disposition of the Kingdom by, it is not so long since we had an opportunity of feeling the Pulse of the Nation; but that we may reasonably conclude, that all other things remaining as they did, the temper and complexion of the generality of the people, is also much the same. And whensoever His Majesty shall either find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self obliged from the necessity of His Affairs, or from the goodness of His Inclinations be pleased, to call a Parliament, How little will he, upon a disappointment of what he is made to believe and expect, judge himself indebted to those who have so industriously deluded him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. And as they are no ways subservient to His Majesties profit or service; so neither will they in the event prove so useful either to a Popish or Arbitrary design as some do apprehend. Not that any think the King knows of any such design promoted by them; but there are those who may have ends in this, as in the <hi>Dutch</hi>-War and <hi>Black-Heath</hi> Army, which His Majesty is not aware of. But tho' some little creatures may have ultimately aim<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d at some such thing, by promoting of them; yet such villanous designs are, in charity, to be supposed far from the intentions of most that have subscribed them. And accordingly, when divers of the most zealous Actors in the carrying them on, have been calmly told what were the natural and ill tendencies of them, they have solemnly professed, that they would sooner be hanged at their own dores, than be intentionally accessory to the establishing a Despotical Rule over the Nation, or the enslaving the Kingdom to Popery again. Nay, it is to be hoped, that should either or both these, at any time hereafter, more neerly and visibly threaten <hi>England,</hi> many of the present Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dressers will, in their lawful stations, be amongst the most forward and zealous to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand them. Nor will they in such a case find any way to expiate their indiscretion, and attone for their present folly, but by thus demonstrating, that it was no part of their intention hereby to contribute to these things. And should any in the List of the late <hi>Thanksgivin<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> be hereafter found to have promoted Addresses with a prospect of intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing other Tyranny or the Papal worship, the names and pretences of Law and the Protestant Religion, which they have not only flourished their Papers with, but made His Majesties promise of preserving them the ground of their acknowledgments, and the foundation of the Tenders which they have made of their Lives and Fortunes, will <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> infamy upon them, and render them the objects of all mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65195:3"/>and indignation. And in the mean time, the Jealousies and Fears which some are said to have conceived of a Popish and Arbitray Design at the bottom of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresses, do by quickning the watchfulness of the Nation, serve not only to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, but to give them a total disappointment therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. Nor yet in the next place, is the number of the Subscribers so considerable, as to bear any proportion to those who are against them. For tho' a few busie people have made a great noise and buz in several places of the Kingdom, yet all of them put together, make not so great a number as we have seen not long since to one Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for a Parliament. So that it is matter of wonder, that the Government for its own reputation hath not in some publick way prohibited and forbid them, and especially when it finds, that after all the neglect and scorn which the Addressers are exposed to for their paucity and fewness, yet they have not the Discretion to forbear and desist. Sir, you must needs have observed by reading the <hi>Gazetts,</hi> where you have the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventory of them, that almost all the Counties, and the most principal Cities, such as <hi>London</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> and the chiefest <hi>Towns</hi> and <hi>Corporations</hi> have forbore and declined pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting any. And I may add, that even where they have been obtained, not <hi>One</hi> in <hi>Ten,</hi> and in some places not <hi>One</hi> in a <hi>Hundred</hi> had any hand in, or gave concurrence to them. For if it be allowed, as in Justice as well as Modesty it ought, that whosoever have either avoided or refused Subscribing, are as truely to be judged against them, as they who have positively withstood, or directly opposed them, then the <hi>Tale</hi> of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dressers will make but a very small show and appearance in the Muster-roll of the Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. And this is the rather to be taken notice of, and doth the better evidence what opinion the people have of them, if you consider the Means, Ways, Arts and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods that have been used and taken to advance and promote them. For besides that most of the Clergy, and many in the present Commissions both Civil and Military, as well as several of the Magistrates of Corporations, have not only interested themselves in countenancing, but been sticklers for them, as for the great <hi>Charter</hi> or <hi>Petition of Right.</hi> The Grace and Favour with which they have been received, and the Marks and Characters of Honour which have been conferred upon divers that presented them, who for ought the world knows, had no signal matter else to recommend them, were very proper means to have procured an Universal and National Application. And yet neither the Influence of those who pretend to prescribe unto the Understandings, as well as to direct and conduct the Consciences of men; nor the Authority and Advice of those, to whom all are willing to pay a Respect and Obedience, in whatsoever their Interest, Religion, and the Law will suffer them; nor yet the hopes of Titles and Honours, which some merely for that Service have, in the truest sence, been loaded with, have been effectual to prevail with, or bring over any great or valuable number to joyn in them. And should I tell you what other Arts have been pursued to obtain men to Address, you would say, that either a sullen Crossness, or some more generous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple had possessed the Nation, that persons should every where so generally refuse and withstand them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 9. And if you more narrowly enquire into the condition of those that are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in the Addresses, you will find their Quality for the most part as inconsiderable as their Number. The greatest Part of those who have given thanks for Dissolving Parliaments, are such as either for want of Years, or Poverty, were never capable of giving a Vote in Election of Members to sit in them. Setting aside Two or Three, or a few more in a Town or Corporotion that have embark't in them, the greatest part are made up of the Scum and refuse of the place where they live. <hi>Norwich,</hi> whence we have been alarm'd with the greatest noise, yields but a small number of persons either of Estate of Usefulness, whose hands were annexed to the Paper which was sent up.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 10. Nor is the Moral Condition of the Addressers disagreeable to to their Civil: For not to mention, that those who are most Popishly inclined, have enrolled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves among the first in the respective Lists and Subscriptions, several others of them are such who were formerly either in the number of Abhorrers of Petitions, or guilty of one Offence or another, which the last Parliments were about calling them to an account for. And wheresoever there is either a little bankrupt Tradesman, a scandalous and disgrac d Attorney, one whose Necessity exposeth him to be biased by Crusts of Bread and Pots of Ale, any whose Folly makes them pragmatical and impertinent, or whose Prodigality and Ambition forceth them to look for Preferment beyond their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, these are infallibly in the front of the Addressers, and the unwearied and industrious procurers of Thanks to His Majesty for Dissolving Parliaments. So that for many of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65195:4"/>them, their manners are such, that did the King but truly understand what Character they pass under where they are known, He would esteem it a reflection upon His Honour, and an aspersion upon the Wisdom and Equity of His proceedings, to be either approached or thanked by them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 11. And as for their Politicks, they are in most of them proportionate to their Morals, and agreeable to the condition which their Birth, Education and Fortune have stated them in. For can any man believe that the <hi>Mayors, Headboroughs, Aldermen, Bailiffs, Burgesses</hi> and <hi>Freemen</hi> of <hi>Rippon, Wigan, Windsor, Chatham, Haslemere, New-Sarum,</hi> &amp;c. are competent Judges of what the late Houses of Commons did Legally or Illegally? Of what is according or contrary to the Laws and Customs of Parliament? Or what is agreeable or disagreeable to the Fundamental Constitution of the Land, which as well limits the Prerogative of the King, as fixeth the Rights, Liberties, and Authority of Lords and Commons; when almost all the <hi>Ancients</hi> and <hi>Benchers,</hi> and most of the <hi>Barristers,</hi> as well as <hi>Students</hi> of the several <hi>Inns</hi> of Court have declared, that they are things above them, and which they have neither Power nor Ability to make a determination concerning? Surely the Learned <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of the <hi>Gown</hi> are at least as well qualified to give their Sense and Opinion about these matters, as Country <hi>Mercers, Innkeepers, Taylers</hi> and <hi>Thatchers</hi> are; and yet those refuse to meddle with Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresses as referring to things which appertain not unto them, whilst the latter make themselves Arbitrators between the King and Two Parliaments, and from their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Wisdom pass Sentence against their Representatives. The Gentlemen of the Long-Robe have besides their Loyalty, wherein none dare pretend to outstrip and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed them, as great obligations arising from Interest to have sway'd to accommodate themselves to the wishes and desires of the Court in this matter, as any persons in the Nation have; And therefore it can be nothing but their knowledg of, and their value for the Laws of the Kingdom, with the Reverence which they are ever resolved to maintain for Parliaments, that could have made them oppose Addresses, and thereby venture the displeasing those, to whom they owe, and from whom they expect so much. Nor will Twenty Thousand Hands to Addresses from Country-Corporations, make that Impression upon the minds of modest and thinking men, as their being cast out and refused by the <hi>Benchers</hi> and <hi>Barristers</hi> of the <hi>Inns</hi> of Court.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 12. Having thus far acquainted you with my freest and most natural Thoughts in general about them, it is time now that we more neerly inspect and pass our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the matter of them: and if I mistake not, the presuming to give His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty Thanks for <hi>His promising to Govern by Law,</hi> is no less than a Disloyal and gross Reflection upon him. For will not some men hereupon think that he hath Administred some just ground of Fear or Belief, as if he intended to Govern Arbitrarily? Or doth it not insinuate that he is so unconfin'd, that if he please he may do so? Or may we not say, that it plainly intimates, that the best Security which we have to rely upon why he will not, is His Royal Word in His late Declaration? It doth unbeccme <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish</hi> Subjects to thank their Prince for promising to Govern by Law; seeing as he never did, so he cannot do otherwise. His Ministers may act Illegally, and they are liable to answer for it; but he can do nothing but what the Law directs and justifies. Nor is he only bound to this by his Coronation-Oath, which is however a more Sacred and Solemn Tye than a Promise in a Declaration; But his own Greatness, and his very Prerogative, as having their own Foundations in the Law, oblige him to it. For as <hi>Bracton</hi> says, <hi>Rex habet superiorem Legem per quam factus est Rex,</hi> Lib. 3. de Action. Cap. 9. Sect. 3. and therefore that <hi>Lex froenum est Regis potentiae,</hi> The Law bounds and limits the Kings Power. <hi>Nor can he,</hi> says <hi>Fortescue</hi> De Leg. Angl. <hi>Govern his People by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Power, than the Law.</hi> And as <hi>Bracton</hi> expresseth it, <hi>(ubi supra) Rex nihil potest, nisi id s<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lum quod de jure potest;</hi> The King can do nothing, but what he can do by Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 13. But you will the less marvel at their returning His Majesty Thanks for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mising to Govern by Law, seeing the Tenor of all the Addresses is to intimate, That all the Right or Claim which we have by Law in our Lives, Liberties or Estates, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent upon His Majesties Will and Pleasure. This all of them suggest and insinuate, and some of them do very fully express.<note place="margin">Addr. from <hi>Coatham.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Da<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Addr. from <hi>B<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rost<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Addr. from <hi>H<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>st<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> What else can be meant by their thanking His Majesty, <hi>For his untarallel'd Grace, Favour and Goodness, in purposing to continue to them their just Rights, Liberberties and Properties?</hi> And <hi>for his Resolution, that (notwithstanding many Provocations yet His Majesty will Govern in all things according to the Laws of the Kingdom? And for His Princely Purpose, never to invade the Liberties of his Subjects?</hi> And that he hath declared, <hi>He will never use Arbitrary Government?</hi> Do not these and all
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65195:4"/>the other Addresses imply, That tho' the Laws speak of Rights, Liberties and Properties which belong unto us; yet they are not secured unto us, but that His Majesty, were it not for the just and gracious temper of his Nature, might invade and destroy them? And is not this to sacrifice, as far as in them lies, <hi>Magna Charta, Petition of Right,</hi> and our <hi>Statute</hi> and <hi>Common-Laws,</hi> to the Soveraign Will and Arbitrary pleasure of the Prince? Whereas, thanks be to God, the King can neither disseise a man of his Liberty, nor break in upon his Property; but we are enabled to relieve our selves in His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Courts. Nor are these men, for all their seeming to abandon Themselves, Lives, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Properties to His Majesty's Will, to be too much trusted or relied upon by His Majesty, should he be tempted contrary to his Duty and Inclination, to offer at any thing Illegal, considering how unjustly clamorous they have been against the House of Commons, <hi>For their Illegal Votes and Orders, and usurping upon their Persons and Estates.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Addr. from the Westren Division of <hi>Sussex</hi> Addr. from <hi>Exon.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Norwich.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>For Tyrannizing over their Fellow-Subjects. For their Arbitrary Proceedings in the two last Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and their Unlimited and Illegal Imprisonments, and their Messengers exorbitant, exacting, pretended fees contrary to Magna Charta.</hi> For if they be so heated and transported against their own and the Kingdoms Representatives, when very many wise, learned, and indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent persons, and who are as jealous of the least invasion upon the liberty and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Subject, as any in the Nation, think that the House of Commons did nothing in all the Cases that are with so much warmth and resentment reflected upon, but what they both might and ought to do by the Laws of the Land and Parliamentary Presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents; Is it to be imagined, that they would very tamely lose their Lives, or suffer themselves to be silently dispossessed of their Estates, at the sole and indisputable plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of the Prince?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 14. And whereas by all the Addresses they testifie with what approbation they have received His Majesties late Declaration; it is too plain, that thereby they intimate their Satisfaction in the Dissolution of so many Parliaments.<note place="margin">Addr. from <hi>Bristol.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Norwich.</hi>
               </note> Nay some of them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly <hi>publish their unanimous consent and delight therein.</hi> And others return His Majesty <hi>so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn thanks for giving his two last Parliaments such timely Dissolutions.</hi> Had these people the discretion and modesty which might become them, they would have esteem'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves very improper and unsufficient Judges of the prudentialness of that exercise of Royal Power. And this is the first president that ever <hi>England</hi> saw, of any Commoners giving His Majesty thanks for dismissing Parliaments. For tho' some of our former Kings have, upon Misunderstandings arisen between them and their Parliaments, abruptly Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved them, and published very weighty Declarations in Justification of what they did; yet whatever Submission the people yielded to what these Princes had done, or how seasonable and justifiable soever they in their own minds believed it, they never Addres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed these Monarchs in a way of Thanks for doing of it. And tho' possibly the last Long-Parliament, was through its long Sitting, esteemed a great grievance to the Nation, and too many of its Members judged easily manageable for betraying the liberty of the Subject, had they been powerfully tempted thereunto, and tho' His Majesties Dissolving them was entertained with an Universal joy, yet none had the folly to thank him for it, as knowing of what fatal consequence such an action might afterwards prove. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the many acknowledgments which some have returned the King for Dissolving Two such Parliaments, that for what appear by their Printed <hi>Votes</hi> and <hi>Debates,</hi> were filled with men of as great integrity and ability, as well as Gentlemen of as great E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states, as have in any age met together in the great Councel and Senate of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; do become those that are well-wishers to the Protestant Religion either at home or abroad, or such as have duly considered the present state of the Nation and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dangers with which it is encompassed, may be worthy of their most serious thoughts, when they are at leasure to look back upon, and examine what they have done. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly those men, who at the same time thank the King for promising to Govern by Law, never considered that it is both a fundamental Law of the Kingdom, and much of the soul and life of all our Laws, not only to have frequent Parliaments, but have them permitted to sit to dispatch the affairs of the Nation. Nor can they be supposed to have seriously weighed how when the Kingdom seems in so much danger from an aspiring and formidable Neighbour, our Religion and Lives so greatly in hazard by the hellish conspiracies of the Papists, our Allies in so much need of countenance and assistance, that the King, tho' never so well inclined, as we will always believe His Majesty to be, cannot without the concurence, aid and advice of a Parliament, do any thing may ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually answer those weighty, importunate and loud calls. For what can His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty be conceived able to do in such circumstances, when he hath neither Power over
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65195:5"/>the Purses of his people, nor can so much as command the <hi>Militia</hi> of the Nation to march out of their respective Counties? But that which these Addresses imply, which is yet of more dangerous importance, is that the very Being of Parliaments doth wholly depend upon the will and pleasure of the King. Whereas such a supposal is inconsistent with the constitution of the Kingdom, does no way comport with the ends of our Government, and might prove very dangerous to the safety and happiness of the Nation, in case we should hereafter have a King void of compassion to, and regardless of the interest of his people. For tho' it be left to the Wisdom of the Soveraign where he will have Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments to Assemble, and belongs to His Prerogative to call them when his own Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly occasions or the necessities of his people do require; yet the Law which His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty is sworn to observe,<note place="margin">4 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.36. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</note> it being a part of His Coronation Oath, <hi>Tenere Leges &amp; consue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudines Regni,</hi> doth both provide that we shall have <hi>Annual</hi> Parliaments, and by directing the ends for, and the affairs about which they are to meet, doth at least imply some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of their continuing to sit till those affairs be accomplished, and the said ends com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed and obtained. Nor will His Majesty be ever induced to believe that he can be thought to Govern according to Law, without calling Parliaments whensoever the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresses and grievances of His people bespeak and require them. Neither is it to be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined that he should long harbour any such thought in His Royal breast, That he can answer the directions and ends of the Law, without permitting Parliaments to sit such a convenient season, as that they may in conjunction with His Majesty, relieve the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from their manifold fears, redress the numerous and sore grievances of the Nation, and provide for the safety, strength, and honour of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 15. In the next place, All the Addresses seem to be fram<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d towards the expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing a willingness in the People, that the Duke of <hi>Yorke</hi> should succeed His Majesty. And this they insinuate a readiness in the Addresses to further, without the Ieast desire to have any provision made before-hand for the Security of the Protestant Religion, or Safe-guarding the Lives of such as profess it, under the Reign of one that is a known and violent Papist.<note place="margin">Addr. from the County of <hi>Somerset.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Cambridge, Ripon,</hi> West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern Division of <hi>Sussex.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Hertford.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Monmuth,</hi>
               </note> For whilst the Addressers are pleased to say, <hi>That it is the Kingdoms Interest to continue the Succession in its Due and Right Line;</hi> And take upon them to thank His Majesty, <hi>For his unalterable Resolutions to preserve the Crown in its due and Legal course of Descent; and undertake to sacrifice their Lives to preserve the Kings Heirs and lawful Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors.</hi> And <hi>offer their Lives and Fortunes to His Majesties Disposal for this purpose;</hi> All peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple do sufficiently understand what they aim at, and that the meaning-of all this is, That they would have the Duke of <hi>York</hi> come to the Throne. But I wish they had shown so much Ingenuity and Candour, as to have taken notice and acknowledged, that all His Majesties Subjects are as tender of the Preservation of the Monarchy, and as zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to have it continued in the Royal Line, as any of themselves dare pretend to be. For it is more than probable, that nothing so much influenced the bringing in and pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the <hi>Bill of Exclusion,</hi> as a regard to the Preservation of the Monarchy; which some of the best, wisest, and most Loyal of His Majesty's Subjects think the coming to have a Popish King may shake and endanger; especially considering what this Nation felt from the last Papist that possest the Throne; and how it hath been of late, and still is threatned by the bloody Conspiracies of the <hi>Romish</hi> Party. Besides, it had not been amiss, if our late Addressers had owned, that the King, Lords and Commons have a Power to dispose of the Succession, as they shall judge most conducible to the Safety, Interest and Happiness of the Kingdom; and that he is His Majesties Heir and Successor, upon whom the whole Legislative Power shall think meet to settle the Inheritance of the Crown. Nor would it have misbecome men professing the <hi>Protestant</hi> Religion, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>English</hi> Liberties, to have recommended to His Majesties second Thoughts and maturer Advice, what Three several Parliaments have with so much strength of Reason insisted upon, and with so much earnestness pursued and desired. And I wish they were able to tell us what they mean, when at the same time that they engage to defend the <hi>Protestant</hi> Religion, they vow, <hi>to the last drop of their Blood, to stand by the next Successor;</hi> And the rather, because there is some reason to believe, that many of them will not be over-forward to dye Martyrs. It would be also some satisfaction to be instructed, how they think <hi>to defend the Crown,</hi> in the Preservation whereof they pretend to be ready <hi>To sacrifice themselves and all they have;</hi> seeing by being willing to admit a Papist to be King, they consent to the robbing it of the <hi>Supremacy,</hi> which is one of the brightest Jewels in it. However it is some comfort, that one end of setting on foot and carrying on these Addresses, being to make a <hi>Survey</hi> and obtain a <hi>List</hi> of all that were for the <hi>Duke of York,</hi> they do not upon the <hi>Muster-Rolls</hi> appear so many as to endanger the Nation in a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65195:5"/>
               <hi>Civil War,</hi> in case the King should hereafter so far comply with the humble Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests of his People, as to be willing to pass the <hi>Bill of Exclusion,</hi> if tendred to him by a future Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 16. But besides what is already said concerning the Quality and Design of the the said Addresses, there is this farther tendency in them all, namely, to insinuate to the Nation, that we have and enjoy a sufficient Security for our Religion, Lives and Liberties. For as if it were not enough to acknowledge,<note place="margin">Addr. from <hi>Derby,</hi> and from the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of <hi>Surry</hi> Addr. from <hi>Bristol,</hi> and from <hi>Dorset.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Lynn Regis, Clifton, Dart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth, Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness;</hi> Grand Inquest of the County of <hi>Oxon, Bristol,</hi> &amp;c.</note> as all His Majesties Liege-people do, <hi>His Majesties Easie, Just, and most Gracious Government since His Restora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and to testifie their sense of the Felicity and Happiness which all His Majesties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects have most comfortably enjoyed under a most Regular, Gracious and Peaceful Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> They are pleased further to adde, His that Majesties Promise in His late Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Of adhering to the Laws of the Land and making them the Rule of His Government, is not only sufficient to allay all mens Fears and Jealousies, remove the Misunderstandings of all well-meaning and reasonable People, and give us all possible assurance of enjoying the greatest Liberty and best Religion, that any people in the world have; but that no greater Security can be had or hoped for, in order to the enjoying our Religion, Liberties and Properties, than His Majesties Royal Word to Govern by the Laws.</hi> Whereas not only four Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have represented and declared the manifold Dangers by which our Religion, Lives and Properties are threatned and encompassed; and how difficult, if not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible it is, to preserve and secure them from the Designs that are laid against them; but the King also hath been pleased to signifie the same, and that as well in several Proclamations published for the informing of His People, as in divers Speeches to His Two Houses of Parliament; whose Advice He both thereupon required, and also that effectual Laws might be made for the obviating and preventing those many Mischiefs and Dangers that are impending over us. And if the Kings hitherto governing by Law, hath not been sufficient to discourage our Popish Enemies from Conspiring our Destruction; Can it be apprehended, that His Majesties <hi>adherence to the Laws</hi> for the future, will remove the Jealousies, and allay the Fears which we have of the Papists? Besides, tho' His Majesty is always to be supposed, resolved and inclined to Govern by Law, yet there want not too many Instances, wherein His Ministers that are trusted with the Administration of Justice, have to the great prejudice of the Subject, and the Alarming the whole Nation, failed in their Duty. Our dreadful Apprehensions do not proceed from any ill Opinion which we have of the King, but from the impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Hatred which the <hi>Romish</hi> Faction bear as well against Him, as His Protestant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; and from the Corruption of those Officers of Justice, who do either abuse or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the Law to base Ends, or hinder its due and Legal Execution. Nor is it our having good Laws, but their being truely executed, that will advantage and relieve us; &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are to be pardon'd, tho' we profess our selves doubtful of our Security by them, whilst some that have been entrusted with the Administration of them, are sufferd to escape the punishments which they have deserved for obstructing their course, and for perverting of them. And what if we should with all Thankfulness acknowledg, that we are in some Security during His Majesties Life, will the Laws which we have, without some farther and more effectual provision before His Majesties Death, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute much to our Safety, when we shall hereafter have a <hi>Popish</hi> King to Reign over us? But can these men be supposed in earnest, when they tell us that the Nation is in no danger, while the Papists continue so active to extirpate the <hi>Northern Heresie,</hi> and are in a more hopeful way to effect it than ever? Alas! the <hi>Popish Plot,</hi> instead of being defeated, is not so much as yet throughly detected: And instead of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists</hi> bein<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dismay'd by that Discovery which hath been made, or by the Justice which hath been inflicted upon some of the Criminals, they are only enflam<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to prosecute their Devilish Conspiracy with the greater vigour, and to execute what they intend with more bloody rage. Can any man that is not void of common sense believe, that we are safe aad out of danger, when every true Protestant is in daily hazard through their Sham-Plots, and by their hiring and suborning vile and execrable Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains to Swear Treason against those that have any Zeal for our Religion and Civil Liberties? How can we be supposed arrived at any measure of Safety, when there are an Hundred things absolutely necessary to be done towards our Preservation, wherein the King, tho' fully disposed <hi>to adhere to the Laws,</hi> is in no capacity to meddle, without the assistance and concurrence of his Parliament? And therefore if men will after all that they have seen, felt, heard, and read of a Damnable Popish Plot to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the Person of the King, overthrow the Established Religion, and enslave the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65195:6"/>Nation to an Antichristian forraign Power, flatter themselves upon a bare Declaration, that His Majesty will <hi>Govern by Law,</hi> that thereupon all is safe and secure; they must not take it ill, if they be thought accessary to their own and the Kingdoms ruine, through their dull and blockish Incredulity, to say no worse.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 17. Another ill tendency of most, if not all the Addresses, is the reviving the memory of the late unhappy Troubles, which it is the Interest both of His Ma esty and the whole Kingdom to have buried in perpetual Oblivion. For the mentioning of that War with reflection and bitterneses, serves only to make men remember three hasty Dissolutions of Parliaments, and Twelve years want of one, with some other things which fell out in that space, all which preceded and had too great an influence towards the causing of it. Besides, there was a Massacre of the Protestants in <hi>Ireland</hi> by the Papists there, and a bloody War commenced for the extirpation of the English Government in that Kingdom; which as it too much exasperated the minds of men towards that unhappy War which begun here, so I fear the upbraiding men too much with their concern in those Troubles, will not prove very useful to the party that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears most forward in it. Nor is it easie to be imagined, how the mention of the late War comes to be brought upon the Stage at this time of day, seeing most that were believed either the first Fomenters of, or proved afterwards Actors in it, are dead and gone; and for their Children (witness many of the most violent and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flown Clergy) they are commonly found to be of Principles directly contrary to what they were. Nay, that which renders all reproachful Discourse of that War at this juncture still more strange, is that the ignominy and <hi>odium</hi> of it is designed to fall upon many of the chiefest of those that served under the Banners of the late King, or upon such who sprung from them that did, and have their Fathers Loyalty mixed with their Blood. And to deal plainly, I know nothing that can so plausibly justifie the Parliaments cause in that War, as the telling the World that there was little or no difference betwixt their Principles and the Principles of those that sat in the Two last Parliaments, whose actings the Addresses do with so much Indecency brand and asperse. And the language that is daily bestowed upon the Members of these late Parliaments, as being men of the same complexion that they of the Parliament Forty One were, will, instead of leaving any reproach upon them on whom it is intended to be fastned, beget a better opinion of those to whom they are compared, than the Addressers would be willing that they of this Age should find reason to entertain. I may add, that none have lived more peaceably, and with better Submission under His Majesties Government, than they who were engaged on the Parliaments side in that unhppy War; and therefore it doth not seem an act of any great Prudence to discourage them in their Obedience, by upbraiding them with that, which the Law hath not only pardoned, but which they have expiated by their Loyalty since. Nor do I think that when the Parliament, after the King's Restaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, made the Act of <hi>Indemnity,</hi> wherein among other things Enacted which they judged necessary towards the Settlement of the Nation, they prohibited, under a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty, one man s reproaching another with his being concerned in that War, during the space of three years after the date of the said Act, that ever they intended, that men should afterwards with the greatest Licenciousness and Scurrility upbraid one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other with it. Nay, they hop'd, that if the Spirits and Tongues of men were so long bridled and restrain'd, their Animosities would be wholy extinguished before the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piration of that time. And none but men of very implacable Spirits would call over, and with so much <hi>Satyr</hi> asperse men for these things; especially when there hath not been the least cause administred for it: unless it be, that such have a greater <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enderness and value for the Protestant Religion and <hi>English</hi> Liberties, than to desire they should come to lye at the discretion of a Popish Prince, as the Addressers plainly wish they may.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 18. As our Affairs are now circumstanced, and as the state of the Protestant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion stands at present in <hi>England,</hi> the Addressers carry another ill Design in them, which is, to enflame differences further among our selves, and thereby betray us into the hands of Popish Adversaries. For as if the principal thing we were to aim at, were not the preserving our Religion against the Conspiracies of the Papists, and as if the united strength of all Protestants were not little enough to effect and obtain it; no less will serve most, if not all of the late Addressers, than the Executing the Laws with the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most Severity against Protestant Dissenters. And as if there very thinking of a Fanatick had made them <hi>delirous,</hi> they will not allow the Parliament to make the least abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the terms of Conformity, or to give Indulgence in, or dispense with one Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65195:6"/>though all the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and the present <hi>Form of Worship,</hi> and the very <hi>Hierarchy</hi> it self, can plead no other Authority by which they are enjoined, or by which the Subjects of this Land are bound to comply with and submit to them, but some Acts of Parliament. Nay, so little do the persons, that have Subscribed the Addresses, understand the Interest of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant</hi> Religion, as now by Law established, that they would not have an Act to be repealed, which may under a Popish Prince, &amp; in case Popery come to be set up, prove as fatal and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous to them that are at this time the Conformable Clergy, as it will to the Dissenters; tho' at present it do only reach and be applied to the latter. And that I may not seem to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose upon them, Is not all this the full and plain import of their joining <hi>Popish Recusants</hi> and <hi>Seditious Sectaries</hi> all along together?<note place="margin">Address from <hi>Ripon.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Salisbury.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Clifton, Dart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth, Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> &amp;c. Add. from <hi>Norwich.</hi> Addr. from the Western Division of <hi>Sussex.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Norwich.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Ripon.</hi>
               </note> Of their affirming <hi>Fanatical</hi> Parties to be as dangerous as <hi>Popish?</hi> Of reckoning up the <hi>pernicious</hi> endeavours of the <hi>Sectaries,</hi> in consort with the Devilish Designs of the Papists? And as if this ware not sufficient to declare what they mean, they not only take upon them to thank His Majesty, <hi>For not passing Limitations or Nullifications of such wholesom Acts as were designed for Preservation of the Reformed Religion, especially the</hi> 35. <hi>of Q.</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>and for not suffering that Law, and others made against Conventicles to be Repealed: but they humbly pray His Majesty, that those Laws now in force, may vigorcusly, speedily and equally be put in Execution against all Papists and Protestant Dissenters:</hi> And particularly, <hi>that the Statutes of the</hi> 3d <hi>of K.</hi> James, <hi>and the</hi> 35th <hi>of Q.</hi> Elizabeth <hi>may be put and continued in their due Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> It is something strange to find a company of men so zealous for the Protestant Religion, when divers of them are the Disgrace and Reproach of any Religion which they take upon them to profests. But can we believe that they are Protestants, or at least that they understand the Protestant Interest, who represent Dissenters as equally dangerous to the Government and Established Religion, as the Papists are? It would administer a ground of too ill an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of our Supreme Rulers and Publick Ministers, should they allow and approve what these men have suggested. For are there any amongst the Dissenters, that have sworn Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to a <hi>Forreign</hi> Power, that they should be thus put into the same List of dangerous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to the Government with the Papists? Or is there any Security that the Legislative Power can require of them for their Peaceableness, that they are not willing and ready to give? Yea, Is not the Religion of the Dissenters established by Law, as well as that of the Conformists, tho' there be some things Ordained, as the Accoutrements and Modes of the National Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which the Non-Conformists cannot submit unto? For as the only Foundation upon which the Dissenters go, is that their Faith and Worship are agreeable and according to the Scripture, which is the alone Rule of the mind of God to all his People in what they are to believe and perform: So from the Authority which the Scripture hath allowed unto it by the Law of this Land, and by the Consonancy of their Doctrine to the Establish'd Articles of Faith, they humbly conceive that they have the countenance and warranty of the Law for their Religion. Nor doth the Law disallow or forbid any thing which they profess; it only enjoyns some further things, which they cannot come up to. And as the Dissenters do not oppose any one Doctrinal Article of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> so they blame and judge no man for the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Obedience that they promise to the Bishops, or their Conformity to the Ceremonies; but merely beg that themselves may be excused. And should they be gratified as to all which in our present circumstances they do desire, it would amount only to this, That they may Preach the Gospel without being liable to Imprisonment, Fin<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and Banishment. Nor do they covet Ecclesiastical Preferments, or Parochial Maintainance; tho were it not for some things, which are made the <hi>Tests</hi> to those Places and Advantages, and which without any inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency might be laid aside, there are many of them that are as worthy of them as others. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can that which is stiled the Church of <hi>England</hi> suffer any diminution in the number of its Members by an Indulgence to Protestant Dissenters, having both <hi>this will I give thee,</hi> and thus <hi>saith the Magistrate</hi> on their side, unless the Clergy should fall short in Abilities for their Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and in having <hi>Thus saith the Lord</hi> to plead for them. But how dare these persons, who have subscribed the Addresses, assume the confidence to censure Parliaments, for going about to repeal Laws, which by woful experience have been found not only useless, but inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, both to the Protestant Religion, and the safety of the Kingdom? For as Parliaments have Power to Enact Laws, so they have the same Power to Abolish them, whensoever they find, that instead of answering the Ends which they were made for, they have proved prejudicial to the Common Good. And surely one may humbly say, and that without the least Reflection upon the Grace and Favour with which the Addresses have been received, that two Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, so fairly and unanimously chosen, and consisting of Gentlemen of the chiefest Quality, best Parts, greatest Wisdom, most plentiful Estates, and firmest Integrity to the Interest of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and the Nation, and all, except a few, Zealous Sons of the Church, and unfained Defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the present Hierarchy, Discipline, Forms and Rites of Worship, were in all probability as able and likely to know what will let in or keep out Popery, what will preserve us from, or betray us into the hands and power of the Papists, as Twenty or Thirty persons in a County or Corporation, most of whom are not worth Forty Shillings Freehold a year, and many of them not able to speak Ten words of sense together. But it is easie to conjecture who in divers
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65195:7"/>places set these Addressers at work, and who put that in reference to Protestant Dissenters into so many Addresses, namely, either persons Popishly inclined, that they might thereby continue and heighten our differences, and make us the more easily a prey to <hi>Rome;</hi> or some ignorant Clergy-men, who besides their enmity at Fanaticks, have little else to recommend them to the obtaining a common and civil respect, but their <hi>Cassock</hi> and their <hi>Surplice</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 19. And as if all this that I have with the greatest sincerity and justice represented un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, were not enough to blast the credit of the Addresses, and to expose the weakness and folly of such as have subscribed them; there is something yet further, and which is infinitely more pernicious that they pursue and aim at, namely, to possess His Majesty and the World with a belief, that there is a design carried on by Protestants against the King and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Hence they not only thank His Majesty <hi>For recollecting the several steps and advances by which we were betrayed into our former confusions;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Addr. from <hi>Southwark.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Bristol.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Reading.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Derby.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Monmouth.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Ludlow.</hi>
               </note> but take upon them to observe, that there are some <hi>ill men who labour the subversion of our Religion, Liberties and Properties, under the specious pretence of Reformation, being the same method that they brought to pass all the miseries of Usurpation and Tyranny that this Kingdom lately groan'd under;</hi> and that <hi>being seasoned with the old leaven of Common-wealth Principles, they have endeavoured to make a misunderstanding betwixt His Majesty and his people, and to throw us back into the same confusion we were delivered from by His Majesties happy Restauration;</hi> and that not <hi>only the good order and quiet of the Government hath been most wickedly attempted to be disturbed and shaken, but to be overthrown and utterly subverted, and the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Monarchy it self to be destroyed.</hi> Surely had these persons who presume to suggest this unto His Majesty, known any Republicans or Fanaticks, <hi>who by possessing the people with groundless fears and jealousies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Addr. from some in the <hi>Middle-Temple.</hi> Addr. from the Deputy-Lieuten. <hi>&amp;</hi> of <hi>Somerset.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>would bring us into Anarchy and confusion, or that would subvert the known Laws of the Land, wherein our Religion, Liberty and Property are wound up;</hi> they ought by their Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to have Deposed against them, and given in their Names, that they might be prosecuted and come to suffer according to the greatness and quality of their Crimes. But alas! this was a Province they durst not undertake, and the attempting it would have too palpably laid open their Folly, and exposed their Malice. And because many have deen drawn to set their hands to Addresses, who do not well understand whence this clamour of a <hi>Presbyterian Plot</hi> proceeds, I shall briefly unfold the Mystery that lies at the bottom of all this loud and groundless noise.</p>
            <p>The Papists being charged with a Hellish Conspiracy against the Person of the King, our Religion, Government, and the Lives of all His Majesties Protestant-Subjects, and this being proved against them to the satisfaction of all the rational part of Mankind, as well by their own Papers, as by the Testimonies of many unquestionable Witnesses; an d finding that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their impudent denying it, nor their falsely scandalizing some, and endeavouring to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch and corrupt others of the King's Evidence, could either bring them off from the Scandal of this Plot, or free them from the Punishment, which were a Parliament permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Sit, more of them must undergo; they retreat to this as their last refuge, namely, the amuzing the Nation with the Buz of a <hi>Presbyierian</hi> and <hi>Phanatick</hi> Plot, carried on to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow the Government, and destroy the Monarchy, under pretence of prosecuting a <hi>Popish</hi> Conspiracy. And towards the obtaining credit to this, they not only form'd the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue</hi> of the <hi>Meal-Tub,</hi> but invented the Shams of Sir <hi>Edmond-bury Godfrey</hi>'s murdering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and my Lord <hi>Howard</hi> s penning <hi>Fitz-Harris</hi>'s Libel; which tho' they have shamefully redounded upon themselves, yet having no other Game to play, they are still labouring, partly by suborning Witnesses, and hiring impudent Rascals to swear Treason against Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, and partly by a groundless and impudent clamour, to infect unwary and heedless persons with the perswasion of such a Design. And it is from the Papists that weak and credulous people have taken the scent of a Presbyterian Plot, <hi>And ascribe it to His Majesties Wisdom and Soveraign Authority,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Addr. from <hi>Eye</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>that we are not relapsing into the Miseries and Confusions of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and Usurpation, by the subtile Arttfice and cunning Contrivances of the old Enemies of the Monarchy and the Church, who by the insinuations of Religion, Liberty and Property, prevail upon weak and unwary men, to make them subservient to their Factions and Ambitions Designs.</hi> Surely, these men never considered what a notorious Scandal they have hereby endeavoured to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten, not only upon many of His Majesties peaceable, best and most Loyal Subjects, but what a vile Aspersion they have cast upon the whole Kingdom, which greatly suffers in its Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, by standing represented in the face of all the World, as broken and divided within it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and sinking back again into all Confusion: Nor have they duly weighted what a Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction they lodge upon the King s Government and Conduct, that He who was so lately Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored by the unanimous Consent, and with the universal Joy of all his People, should in so few years have lost the Love and Reverence of so great a number of His Subjects, as are intended here to be accused. Can there be any thing vented to the diminishing His Majesties Reputation more abroad, and for discouraging Forreign Princes and States from entring into those Alliance which are necessary for the good, as well of His Majesties Kingdoms, as of Christendom, and for the lessening the expectation and confidence which those with whom we are in Leage, ought to remain possest with, of our being able to answer the ends of them, than this account which these men present His Majesty with, of the posture of the Nation, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65195:7"/>temper of his People, and which our <hi>Gazettes</hi> have diffused into all Countries? And doth not this also directly tend to the filling His Majesties Protestant-Subjects with Jealousies one of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, thereby to take them off from their watchfulness over, and to weaken their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours against the Papists, who labour no less to destroy the Dissenters, than those that Conform to the National Form of Worship, and to the Establish d Discipline and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and for the withstanding of whose Bloody Designs, and saving our Religion and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the effect of their malicious and desperate Conspiracies, the united Hearts and Hands of all true Protestants will be found little enough? And will not this Character, which the Addresses are pleased to give of the state of <hi>England,</hi> wonderfully embolden that aspiring Monarch, the <hi>French</hi> King, to proceed in his Encroachments upon the Dominions of his Neighbours, as judging himself secure from any check which the King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> can give him? For as His Majesty can be in no capacity to discourage him from further At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts against the Peace of <hi>Europe,</hi> or to hinder his Conquest, but by being great in the Hearts of all his own People, and in a happy Correspondence and Conjunction with his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; so we have reason to fear, that they who endeavour to beget Misunderstandings betwixt His Majesty and his Subjects, and to create in them mutual Distrusts each of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, are either Pensioners of <hi>France,</hi> or under the Conduct and Influence of them that are.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 20. But as if it were not enough for those persons, who have subscribed the Addresses, to fasten so vile a charge as you have heard, upon many of the people, whom the better to reconcile credit to what they say, they are pleased to call <hi>Republicans</hi> and <hi>Fanacicks,</hi> they have also taken the boldness to involve the Two last Parliaments under the guilt of the same crimes and accusations. Accordingly they tell His Majesty, <hi>with what an infinite patience and condescen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he did submit to hear unreasonable jealousies promoted in them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Addr. from <hi>Okehampton.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>illegal courses and proceedings vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated, and all the great and most benign Indulgences of their Srveraigns goodness misrepresented.</hi> And they thank the King, <hi>for His steady resolutions of maintaining the Rights of the Crown,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Addr. from <hi>Norwich.</hi>
               </note> &amp;c. <hi>against the Arbitrary Proceedings of the House of Commons in the two last Parliaments; And for not Signing such Bills as were prepared for His Majesties Subjects to associate to destroy the Succession, and extirpate Monarchy.</hi> Yea, they profess <hi>Their Admiration of His Majesties Princely Wisdom and Councel in the conduct of his Affairs, in obviating</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> by Dissolving Parliaments) <hi>the Designs of the pernicious Enemies of the Church and State.</hi> And declare, <hi>That they cannot but admire His Majesties Transcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Sacred Wisdom, which in that dangerous and confused Juncture, did so seasonably interpose, and so calmly suppress the threatning Flames which were breaking forth.</hi> And thereupon they present their Acknowledgments to His Majesty, <hi>For timely preventing</hi> (by Dissolving those Parliaments) <hi>the Designs of Ill men, who in the same Age a second Time attempting by the same Methods as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, the destruction of His Loyal Subjects, the diminution of his Lawful Power, and the debasing the Grandeur of the</hi> English <hi>Throne.</hi> I know not by what Name these false and slanderous Accusati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons charged upon two Parliaments, ought to be called; but it is to be hopd, that the next Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament will at once tell the Nation, by what name the Law stiles them, and what Punishment it hath allotted for those that have made themselves Guilty of so vile and scandalous an Asper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, as that two Parliaments had gone about to destroy the Protestant Religion, as Legally established, and to extirpate Monarchy. Whereas those excellent persons, of which the two last Houses of Commons consisted, had many of them ventured their Lives, and lost their Estates for the Monarchy; and all of them were such, as upon Principles of Reason and from Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation are true Lovers of it. They not only had too late and sad Experience of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, to be fond of returning to it again; but they know, that no other Government can agree with the Genius of the People, and suit the ballance of the Nation, but a well-Regulated Monarchy, such as ours is by the Laws of our Constitution. Nor can His Majest be supposed to believe, that ever they will prove true to the Monarchy, who are not true to the Rights and Priviledges of Parliament. For they who can revile and despise one Essential part of the Constitution, have nothing to oblige them to adhere to the other, but the prospect of Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or worldly Gain. And to see men countenanced, that revile any one part of the Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slative Authority, may be too ill a president, and which His Majesty is obliged to see redressed, from the Love that he beareth to the Crown. For whosoever strikes at Parliaments, does by undermining the Government as by Law Established, shake the very Pillars of the Throne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 21. Nor do they only intimate a Design carried on against the Government, but they insinuate a Change to be made by Force; and upon that supposal, while we are in, and to the apprehensions of all sober persons, likely to continue in perfect Peace, they offer their Lives and Fortunes to the disposal of one part of our Legislative Constitution and Power, in opposition to another. <hi>We yield,</hi> say they, <hi>our Lives and Fortunes at Your Majesties Command,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Addr. from <hi>Winchester.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Bristol.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Cardiffe.</hi> Addr. from <hi>Monmouth:</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>and will to the last drop of our Blood, and Penny of our Fortunes, stand by your Majesty in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Your Royal Person, Crown and Government, and Lawful Successors.</hi> So that by reading the Addresses, one would be inclined to think, that these men construe the King's Declaration, as the Erection of the Royal Standard; and that they intend these Papers for the Muster-Rolls of those that are to fight under His Majesties Ensigns: But as we hope that His Majesty will never have occasion for War, unless it be in relieving his Allies abroad against the Ambition of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65195:8"/>
               <hi>France,</hi> who to all his other Invasion upon the Dominions of his Neighbours, is at this time about employing his Forces against the Subjects of His Majesties Kinsman, the Prince <hi>Palatine;</hi> so we hope, that both in that Case, and in any other, wherein His Wisdom and Justice will suffer Him to engage, He shall not only have the Treasure of all his People, through the Gift of a Parliament, at His Command; but all their Persons and Lives ready to be Sacrificed in His Service. It is no marvel that such thirst after War, who have little to live upon in Time of Peace, and who may expect to be Gainers by Troubles: But His Majesty, who besides the care He is to to have of the Lives and Estates of all his Subjects, hath more to lose Himself alone, than all his People, will not, I judge, be prevailed upon to hearken to rash and heady Councels. And how unequal ought they to apprehend themselves to the Body of the Nation, who when they have had the Folly and Confidence to present an Address in the Name of a whole County,<note place="margin">Address from <hi>Bedfordshire.</hi>
               </note> have at the same time acknowledg d, That they were not able to carry it for any that His Majesty might be inclined to recommend, to serve in the next Parliament for the Shire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 22. The last thing I would observe concerning the Addresses, is their making small numbers of men without previous advice had, with each other, and without being authorised or entrusted, to judge of the State of the Kingdom. For tho it be lawful for any one man, and much more for any number of men, to represent to His Majesty their own wants and dangers, and accordingly beg redress and relief; yet to declare the State of the Nation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to no number of private persons whatsoever, but appertains only to the Parliament, as being the Representative of the whole Kingdom. And therefore the Addressers, by assuming to themselves a Right and Authority to determine about the State of the Nation, and to judge concerning those things which the <hi>Trustees</hi> of all the people met in the great Councel, are only proper and by Law allowed to meddle with, have in my apprehension made too near an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the altering the whole Government. And as they must expect that the judgment which they have passed upon persons and things will at one time or another come under a review; so matters which have either been misrepresented by them, or in reference to which Parliaments have been arraigned, may before then, come to be so well understood by His Majesty, and all things so well adjusted between him and his people, that the Addressers may neither find themselves able to decline, nor be in a condition to controll the jurisdiction of the next Parliament, to which we shall at present leave them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 23. But whereas you may be ready to enquire, that if the Addresses be so pernicious, both in the subject matter and tendency of them, and so contrary to the general sense of the Nation, as I have declared; why the people do not by Petitions from all parts of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom let the King know so much? This I shall return you a just and true answer unto, and then discharge you from any further trouble.</p>
            <p n="1">1st. It is the nature and temper of some men most to disserve the cause, and prejudice the interest which they have espoused, when they are quietly let alone to run their course and to take their full swing. For according to the old Proverb, Give some people Rope enough and they will Hang themselves. The only way to know what they would be at, was for others to look silently on a while. And through giving them scope, their own madness &amp; folly hath made them more ridiculous, than any opposition whatsoever from others could have rendred them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly,</hi> The Petition first from my <hi>Lord Mayor,</hi> the <hi>Court of Aldermen,</hi> and the <hi>Common-Councel</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and then from the <hi>Common-Hall,</hi> is a Copy of what all the Nation would say. In <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> as in a Glass, we see the face of the whole Kingdom: For being the <hi>Epitome</hi> as well as <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis</hi> of the Nation, whatsoever it says, is a compendious expressing of the sense of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly,</hi> Men have been willing to forbear Petitioning, lest by the disparity in the numbers to Petitions and to Addresses, some, thinking all safe through the consideration of the multitude that aim'd at what themselves did, might grow more secure than their dangers will well al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; and lest others upon the same inducement might have taken occasion to grow more insolent than their duty and interest obligeth them unto.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4thly,</hi> His Majesty having received the Addresses with that favour which he did, wise men thought it best not to administer occasion of his refusing Petitions that they foresaw would come accompanied with more hands. It is good manners in Subjects not to grate too hard upon their Prince; but if he have done any thing wherein they can't acquiesce with that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment which they desire, to give him time and liberty to recollect himself.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5thly,</hi> If Petitions shall be judged either necessary or convenient, it is not so late but that they may be yet set on foot. And if it should prove uneasie for any to find it so, they must blame themselves, who by their unwearied carrying on of Addresses, make it needful for His Majesties good Subjects at last to undeceive him, which they can no other way do, at least till a Parliament come, but by Petitions. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <lb/>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your most ready and<lb/> Humble Servant.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>June 28. 81.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Baldwin,</hi> 1681.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65195:8"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>